Hello, and welcome to Lesson 19 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
大家好 欢迎来到本次与沃尔夫兰大学合作的微积分入门第19课
The topic for this lesson is asmyptotes. Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
本节课的主题是渐近线  我们先来简单介绍一下本课的内容
In the past, we have learned how to calculate the limits of functions at points.
在过去 我们已经学会了如何计算函数在点上的极限
For example, if I said find the limit of 3x as x→2, then the answer of course is just 6.
例如 如果我说找3x的极限为x→2，那么答案当然只是6
But you can also take limits at positive or negative infinity. For example, if you said
但你也可以在正无穷或负无穷处取极限  例如 如果你说
a limit of 3x as x→∞, the answer is ∞. At –∞, just the opposite happens; you get back –∞.
3x的极限为x→∞，答案为 ∞  在 -∞ 时 刚好相反 你得到的是 -∞
Now the nice thing is that although you might have infinite limits, the actual answer might be finite.
不错的是虽然你可能有无限的限制 但实际的答案可能是有限的
In this case, you have the limit of 1/x as x→∞ going to 0. There are various kinds of
在这种情况下 你有1/x的极限 因为x→∞ 趋近于 0
of interesting behaviors taking place at infinity, and these are so-called end behaviors of functions.
有各种各样在无穷大处发生的有趣事 这些就是所谓的函数的末端行为
That’s the theme for this lesson, which will be used to sketch graphs eventually.
这就是本节课的主题，最终会用到绘制图像上
Let’s begin with some more motivation and talk about horizontal asymptotes.
我们先再来说说横向渐变
If you look at this table over here, it’s a table for 1/x as x→∞, and you see that as x becomes larger,
如果你看这边的这个表 这是一个1/x的表 因为x→∞ 你看随着x变大
the value of 1/x becomes smaller. As x approaches ∞, 1/x gets closer and closer to 0,
1/x的值越来越小  当x接近 ∞ 时 1/x越来越接近于 0
and hence 0 is a horizontal asymptote of 1/x. You can actually check that in a plot.
因此 0 是1/x的水平渐近线 其实你可以在图中检查一下
You see over here you have the graph of 1/x, and that’s the horizontal asymptote.
你看这里有1/x的图像 这就是水平渐近线
It’s just a horizontal line to which the plot approaches as x→∞.
它只是一条水平线 当x→∞时 剧情向其靠近
Now a more formal definition. The limit of f[x] is L as x→∞ if the value if the values of f[x]
现在来个更正式的定义  当 x→∞ 时 f[x]的极限是L
approach L as x becomes sufficiently large. When you add –∞, the same statement holds,
如果当x变得足够大时 f[x] 的值会接近 L 当你加上 -∞ 时 同样也成立
except that you’re now taking x to be sufficiently large and negative. Then a line y = L
除非你现在把x取为足够大的负值
is a horizontal asymptote of the curve y = f[x] if the limit of f[x] at ∞ or –∞ is L.
如果 f[x] 在 ∞ 或 -∞ 处的极限是 L 那么直线y=L是曲线y=f[x]的水平渐近线
Here’s a plot for the function (x^2 + 1)/(x^2 – 1). When x approaches ∞ or –∞, the values of y
下面是函数(x^2 + 1)/(x^2 - 1)的图像  当 x 接近 ∞ 或 -∞ 时 y 的值将
will approach 1. Roughly speaking, when x is very large, you get (x^2)/(x^2), which is 1.
接近 1  粗略地讲 当x非常大时 你会得到 (x^2)/(x^2) 也就是1
Okay. Now let’s talk about the opposite behavior where you do not have a finite answer at ∞,
好了 现在我们来谈谈相反的情况 即在 ∞ 处没有有限的答案
you have infinite limits at ∞. Here’s a very simple example which we saw earlier on as well.
你在 ∞ 处有无限的极限 这里有一个很简单的例子 我们前面也看到了
When you take the limit of 3x as it approaches ∞, the answer is ∞.
当你把 3x 的极限接近 ∞ 时 答案是 ∞
Just the opposite happens at –∞, so the plot over here has no horizontal asymptotes.
只是在 -∞ 处发生了相反的情况  所以这边的图没有水平渐进性
Okay. Now one might talk about the laws of limits at ∞ just as before. You remember that
好了 现在可以像以前一样 谈谈 ∞ 处的极限规律 你还记得
we have talked about mathematical laws that limits obey, and most of these laws
我们已经谈到了极限所遵守的数学规律  而这些规律大多是
also apply to limits at ∞, but you must be a bit careful. The reason why you must be careful is that
也适用于极限 ∞ 处的情况  但你必须小心一点 原因是
now more than ever, you could have things which are both ∞, and when you try to cancel them,
现在比以往任何时候都要可能碰到一些情况  可能有的东西两项都趋近于 ∞  而当你试图消去它们时
you do not get back 0. Here’s an example. You have x^3 – x, and as x→∞, you get ∞ – ∞.
你不会得到趋近于0的结果  这里有一个例子 x^3 - x 由于x →∞ 你得到 ∞ - ∞
But that’s not 0, so you get back a False over here. But if you think of it as being ∞ * ∞,
但结果不是0 所以你在这边得到的是 False (结果为'假') 但如果你把它看成是 ∞ * ∞
then the answer really is ∞. Better still, you could think of this as being x^3
那么答案是 ∞  更好的是 你可以把它看成是 x^3
as very large compared to x, so the answer is ∞.
因为与 x 相比非常大 所以答案为 ∞
Okay. A very important law which you can use for limits at infinity is the following.
好吧 你可以用以下面非常重要的法则来计算无穷大的极限
You look at the limit of (1/x)^r where r is some positive rational number,
你看 (1/x)^r 的极限 其中r是某个正有理数
and if you assume that r is positive, then this limit is always 0. Just the same thing happens at –∞.
而如果你假设 r 是正值 那么这个极限总是0 只是同样的事情发生在 -∞ 处
You get back a 0 over there as well. For example, if you want the limit of 1/x^2
你得到趋近于 0  例如 如果你想知道 1/x^2 的极限
as x approaches either plus or minus infinity, the answer is just 0. This law is the basis of
当 x 接近正无穷或负无穷时 答案就是 0
lot of problem solving which we’ll see in the next few minutes. As my first example,
这是很多问题解决的基础  我们将在接下来的几分钟内看到几个例子  第一个例子
let’s take a rational function. If you want the limit at ∞, then notice that the highest power
让我们取一个有理函数 如果你想在 ∞ 处得到极限  那么请注意
in the numerator and denominator is x^2. You divide by that and use a function called Apart,
分子和分母中的最高幂是是x^2 你除以这个数 然后使用一个叫做Apart的函数
which will break apart the expressions. You see over here that as x approaches ∞,
它可以拆分表达式  你看这里当 x 接近 ∞ 时
by the previous law, both those terms give you 0, and both those terms give you 0 as well,
根据前面的规律 左边的式子(分子)这一部分是 0  右边的式子(分母)这一部分也同样是 0
so the limit of the numerator is just 2—that’s the 2 from here—and the denominator,
所以左边的极限是 2
the limit is just going to be 3. That’s the 3 from over there. To summarize, the limit of this
右边的极限是 3  综上所述
rather difficult-looking function is just 2/3 as x→∞.
当x → ∞  这个看起来很复杂函数的极限只是 2/3
Okay. That’s the rational case, and now let’s take a case where you have the combination of
这就是合理的情况  现在让我们看看这种情况  你有组合的。
a radical and a rational. Okay. Now that’s your function f[x], and notice that the highest power
一个带根号的式子的和一个有理数的式子 这就是函数 &lt;i&gt;f&lt;/i&gt;[&lt;i&gt;x&lt;/i&gt;] 请注意，最高的幂是
is x because you’ve got a square root of x^2 roughly, so if you divide by that, then you see that
是x  因为你已经得到了 x^2 的平方根 所以如果你除以它 你会看到
the numerator will have a limit of √5 as x→∞ and the denominator will have a limit of 2 as x→∞,
当 x → ∞ 分子的极限为 √5  当 x →∞ 分母的极限为 2
so those are the answers separately. Then if you divide them, you get the limit
所以这些都是各自的答案  然后如果你把它们相除
for the entire radical rational expression.
你就会得到整个带 根号的 有理的 表达式的极限值
Finally, let’s take a pure radical. Here is a radical function. The problem is that as x→∞,
最后我们来看看一个纯根式 这里是一个带根式的函数 问题是当 x →∞
you roughly speaking get ∞ – ∞, and you cannot define that. What we do is we work with
你大致上得到 ∞-∞  而你无法定义它 我们要做的是我们用
the conjugate radical and multiply f by it. You see over here that if we simplify it,
的共轭根式 并将其乘以f 你看这里 如果我们把它简化
the answer is just 4. In other words, the function is simply 4/(x + √(x^2 + 4)).
这个答案是 4  换句话说 这个函数只 4/(x+√(x^2+4))
When x becomes very large, the denominator is much larger than the numerator, so the answer is 0
当 x 变得很大时 分母比分子大得多 所以极限的答案为 0
for the limit. You can confirm that with a plot. You see the limit approaches 0 as x→∞.
你可以用一张图来证实这一点 您可以看到，当 x →∞ 时 极限接近 0
Okay. How about compositions? Remember that if you have a composition of f and g
那组成呢？ 记住 如果你有一个由 f和g 组成的组合
and you want to find the limit as x→a, then what you could do is take the limit inside the function f,
你想找极限为 x →a 可以这么说 如果 f 是连续的而且极限存在
so to speak, provided that f is continuous and the limit exists. Here’s an example.
那么你就可以在函数 f 中取极限 这里有一个例子
You have a function Cos[1/x]. That’s the composition. If you look at the inner limit as x→∞,
你有一个函数 Cos[1/x] 这就是构成。如果你把内极限看成 x →∞
then you get back 0. Then if you take the outer limit, you’ll get back a 1 because the cosine of 0 is 1.
那么你就会得到 0 那么如果你取外极限 你会得到一个 1  因为 0 的余弦是 1
Here is a plot of the function, and you see that as x becomes very large, the function value approaches ∞.
这是函数的图 你可以看到 当x变得非常大时 函数值接近 ∞
Okay. Now in the last two slides, I’ll talk about two shortcuts for computing
现在在最后两张幻灯片 我将谈谈计算极限在无穷的有理函数的两个捷径
rational function limits at infinity. There are some special tricks which are
在这个领域有一些特殊的技巧是很值得我们了解的
well worth knowing in this area. For example, if we have a rational function
例如 如果我们有一个有理函数
and the degree of the numerator is less than the degree of the denominator like over here,
而分子的度数小于分母的度数 就像这里
then then whether you are at ∞ or –∞, the answer is going to be 0 because the denominator grows
那么无论你是在 ∞ 还是 -∞  答案都会是 0 因为分母会增大的速度比分子快得多
much more rapidly than the numerator. On the other hand, if the degrees agree
另一方面，如果幂一致
so the degree of the numerator equals the degree of the denominator, then all that you do is
也就是分子的幂等于分母的幂 那么你所做的就是
you look at the leading coefficients and you get back the answer 2/7 in both the cases over here.
你看一下首项系数 在这边的两种情况下 你会得到答案为 2/7
We’ve covered the case of when the degree is less for the numerator than the denominator
我们已经介绍了分子的度数小于分母的情况
and when they are both equal, but the really difficult case is when they are both
和当它们都相等时的情况  但真正困难的情况是当它们都是
slightly different in the sense that the degree of the numerator is greater than
略有不同 分子的幂要大过分母的幂
the degree of the denominator. Now four things can happen. First of all, you have
现在有四种情况可能发生。首先
a positive expression at ∞, so you have x^6 roughly at ∞ and x^2 over here.
在 ∞ 处有一个正值的表达式  所以在 ∞ 处分子有x^6  分母有 x^2
Then as you approach ∞, then both of these become ∞ because the difference
那么当接近 ∞ 的时候 那么这两个都变成了 ∞ 因为不同的是
between the two degrees is even. If, on the other hand, you have a negative expression at infinity,
幂之间是偶数  如果另一方面 你在无穷大处有一个负表达式
–2/3 roughly over here and –2/3 roughly over there, then the answer for both the limits will be –∞.
这里大致是 -2/3  那里大致 -2/3  那么这两个极限的答案将是 -∞
Now on the other hand, if you have an odd difference for the degrees
现在另一方面如果有幂的奇数差
and the function is positive for larger values, then you see that the degree will affect the answer
而且函数的值越大时为正 那么你会发现幂会影响答案
in the sense that we have ∞ at ∞ and –∞ at –∞. After all, roughly speaking, there is x^9 over x^6.
我们在 ∞ 处趋近于 ∞ 在  -∞ 处趋近于 -∞  粗略地讲 x^9 大于 x^6 差为 x^3
That’s x^3, so as x becomes large, you get ∞, and as x becomes very large and negative, you get –∞.
所以当 x 变大时  就会得到 ∞  当 x 变得很大且为负时 就会得到 -∞
Finally, if the function is negative for large values of x, then you see that
最后 如果函数对x的大值为负 那么你会看到
you get the opposite behavior. After all, when x is large, the negative sign becomes important.
你会得到相反结果  毕竟 当x很大时 负号变得很重要
You get –∞ over here and ∞ over here. There are four combinations: both ∞; both –∞;
这边你得到 -∞ 那边得到 ∞  有四种组合：都是 ∞ 都是 -∞
and one of them ∞, one of them –∞; and then the other way around.
而其中一个是 ∞ 而另一个 -∞  最后一种是其中一个是 -∞ 而另一个 ∞
So that’s the end of this lesson. The main point to note is that roughly the same laws hold
那么这节课就到此为止了 要注意的是
for limits at infinity as they do at individual points, but you have to be a bit more careful.
对于无限大的极限和就像他们在各个点上的法则是几乎一样的 但你必须更加小心
There is a special rule which we saw earlier on for rational functional limits at infinity.
有一个特殊的规则  我们在前面看到了无穷大处的有理函数极限
Sometimes you may need to use a bit of algebra to tackle cases where there are radicals,
有时你可能需要使用一点代数来处理有根号的情况
and then multiplying by conjugates might help. In general, it’s really as easy to work at infinity
然后再乘以共轭也许会有帮助 一般来说 在无限远和在有限远的情况下解决问题一样容易
as it is with finite points. With what you’ve learned, the next lesson will talk about sketching curves.
有了所学的知识 下节课将讲曲线的草图绘制
But before you do that, do review this lesson and look at the exercises and be ready for
但在这之前 要先复习一下本课 看看习题
the next lesson on sketching curves. I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.
做好下一节课画图像课程的准备 今天就到这里了 谢谢